这一节，我们看针对一次性密码本的攻击
In this segment, we're gonna look at
attacks on the one time pad, and some
以及使用流密码时需要注意的事项
things you need to be careful with when
you use the stream cipher. But before we
在这之前，我们先简要回顾
do that, let's do a quick review of where
we were. So recall that the one time
一次性密码本通过异或明文和密钥
来加密，这里的密钥
pad encrypts messages by XORing the
message and a secret key, where the secret
和明文一样长。类似地
解密通过异或
key is as long as the message. Similarly,
decryption is done by similarly
密文和密钥来实现
XORing the cipher text, and the same
secret key. When the key is uniform and
当密钥是均匀随机分布时，我们证明了
一次性密码本的理论安全性
random, we prove that the one-time pad has
this information theoretic security that
就是香农的完美安全。显然
问题是密钥要和明文一样长
Shannon called perfect secrecy. A problem
was, of course, the keys are as long as
这导致一次性密码本很难使用
the message, so the one-time pad is very
difficult to use. We then talked about a
我们讨论了如何将一次性密码本实用化
通过使用伪随机数发生器
way to make the one time pad practical by
using a pseudo random generator that
将短的种子扩展成长得多的信息
expands a short seed into a much larger
message and the way a stream cypher
流密码的工作方式是使用
伪随机数发生器，与一次性密码本一样
worked, essentially using a pseudo random
generator, was in the same way as the one
一次性密码本使用真随机序列
time pad, basically, but rather than using a
truly random pad, we used this pseudo
流密码使用伪随机序列，也是
与明文信息一样长的
random pad that's expanded to be as long
as the message from the short key that's
密钥作为发生器的输入
我们说它的安全性
given as input to the generator. We said
now the security no longer relies on
并不依赖于完美安全，因为
流密码不可能是完美安全的
perfect secrecy because stream ciphers
cannot be perfectly secure. Instead
流密码安全性依赖于伪随机数
发生器的性质
security relies on properties of the
pseudo random generator and we said that
我们说伪随机数发生器
必须是不可预测的
the pseudo random generator essentially
needs to be unpredictable, but in fact it
但事实上这个定义使用起来有点困难
turns out that definition is a little bit
hard to work with and we're going to see a
于是我们将看一个PRG安全性更好的定义
用两节的内容
better definition of security for PRGs in
about two segments. But in this segment
这一节我们讨论对一次性密码本的攻击
we're going to talk about attacks on the
one time pad. And the first attack I want to
第一种攻击叫做两次密码本攻击
talk about is what's called the two time pad
attack, okay? so remember that the
记住一次性密码本之所以叫一次
是因为密码本只能加密
one time pad is called "one time" pad because
the pad can only be used to encrypt a
单个信息。我将为大家展示
如果同样的密码本
single message. I want to show you that if
the same pad is used to encrypt more than
为不同的明文加密，就不再安全了
one message, then security goes out the
window, and basically an eavesdropper can
一个窃听者可以完全解密出明文
那么我们看一个例子
completely decrypt encrypted messages.
So let's look at an example. So here we
两个明文信息m1和m2，
使用相同密码本加密
have two messages m1 and m2 that are
encrypted using the same pad. So the
得到密文C1和C2
分别是m1和m2的加密
resulting ciphertext, C1 and C2, again
basically are encryptions of these
使用相同的密码本加密的
messages, m1 and m2, but both are
encrypted using the same pad. Now suppose
现在假设窃听者截获了C1和C2
an eavesdropper intercepts C1 and C2, and
he obtains, he basically has both C1 and C2.
窃听者很自然地计算C1和C2的异或
The natural thing for the eavesdropper
to do is actually compute the XOR of C1
他会得到什么？
and C2 and what does he get when he
computes this XOR? So I hope everybody
大家应该看出，C1异或C2
密码本被异或抵消了
sees that, basically, once you XOR
C1 and C2, the pads cancel out, and
本质上得到的就是两段明文的异或
essentially, what comes out of this is the
XOR of the plaintext messages.
英语实际上有着足够的冗余
And it turns out that English basically
has enough redundancy, such that if I give
导致如果给定两明文的异或
you the XOR of two plaintext
messages, you can actually recover those
是可以完全还原出两个明文的
对我们来说更重要的是
two mesages completely. More importantly
for us is these messages are encoded
这些信息用ASCII码编码
本身就有着足够的冗余了
using ASCII. In fact, ASCII encodings has
enough redundancy, such that given the
给定两个ASCII码信息的异或
可以还原出明文
XOR of two ASCII encoded messages,
you can recover the original messages
本质上，给定这些异或
可以还原出两条明文信息
back. So, essentially, given these XORs,
you can recover both messages. So the
要点是，如果你使用同样的密码本
去加密多条信息
thing to remember here is if you ever use
the same pad to encrypt multiple messages
攻击者截获密文，最终可以
an attack who intercepts the resulting
ciphertexts can eventually recover the
不费力地还原出明文
existing plaintexts without too much
work. So, the stream cipher key or the
所以流密码的密钥使用次数
永远不应超过一次
one time pad key should never ever, ever,
ever be used more than once. So, let's
我们看几个实际当中的例子
look at some examples where this comes up
in practice. It's a very common mistake to
多次使用流密钥是常见错误
use the stream cipher key, or a one time
pad key more than once. Now, let me show
看几个例子，在你自己的系统中
不要再犯这些错误
you some examples where this comes up. So
you know to avoid these mistakes, when you
第一个例子是历史上的
build your own systems. The first example
is a historic example. At the beginning of
1940年代初，苏联使用一次性密码本
the 1940s, where the Russians actually
used a one time pad to encrypt various
加密大量信息。很不幸
密码本由人掷骰子来生成
messages. Unfortunately, the pads that they
were using were generated by a human by
人掷骰子并记录下结果
throwing dice. And so, you know, the human
would throw these dice, and write down the
收集的结果就被用作加密的密码本
results of these throws. And the collected
throws would then form the pads that were
由于生成密码本颇费人工
used for encryption. Now, because it was
kind of laborious for them to generate
只用来加密一条信息就显得很浪费
these pads, it seems wasteful to use the
pads to encrypt just one message. So the
所以最后用来加密多条信息
ended up using these pads to encrypt
multiple messages. And US intelligence was
实际上美国智囊可以截获这些二次密码本
actually able to intercept these two time
pads. These ciphertexts that were
这些密文由不同明文，经相同密码本
加密而成
encrypted using the same pad, applied to
different messages. And it turns out, over
经过几年，他们可以解密约
a period of several years, they we're able
to decrypt something like 3,000 plain
3000条明文，仅凭截获密文即可
这就叫做Venona计划
texts just by intercepting these ciphertexts.
The project is called Project Venona
这是密码分析很精彩的一幕
It's actually a fascinating
of cryptanalysis, just because the two
仅仅因为两次密码本是不安全的
我更想讲一些更近代的例子
time pad is insecure. More importantly, I
want to talk about more recent examples
以网络协议为背景的
看一个Windown NT的例子
that come up in networking protocols, so
let me give you an example from Windows NT,
是关于其点到点传输协议的
in a product called the,
point-to-point transfer protocol. This is
(注意不是Peer-to-Peer)
它是关于客户端希望于服务端安全通信的
a protocol for a client wishing to
communicate securely with a server. The
客户端和服务端共享一个密钥
并且相互通信
client and the server both share a secret
key here, and they both send messages to
这里客户端发送的明文信息记为m1
one another. So, here, we'll denote the
messages from the client by m1. So, the
客户端发送信息，服务端应答
client sends a message, the server
responds, the client sends a message, the
客户端发送信息，服务端应答
server responds, the client sends a
message, the server responds, and so on
等等。。PPTP协议的工作原理
将双方的整个互动
and so forth. Now, the way PPTP works is,
basically, the entire interaction, from
当作一个流，换句话说
the client to the server, is considered as
one stream. In other words, what happens
这里的m1, m2, m3被视作一个长流
is, the messages m1, and m2 and m3, are
kind of viewed as one long stream.
这里双竖线表示联结
Here, these two parallel lines means
concatenation. So, essentially, we're
本质上我们将客户端和服务端的
信息全部联结成一个长流
concatenating all the messages from the
client to the server into one long stream.
整个长流使用流密钥K来加密
And all that stream is encrypted using the
stream cipher with key K. So that's
感觉非常好。并没有错误
perfectly fine. I mean, there's nothing
wrong with that. This messages are
加密的信息被当成一个长流
使用相同密钥加密
encrypted, are treated as one long stream,
and they're all encrypted using the same
问题在于，服务端也在发生着相同的事
key. The problem is, the same thing is
happening also on the server side. In
换句话说，从服务端发出的信息
other words, all the messages from the
server are also treated as one long
它们都被联结起来了
stream. So here, they're all concatenated
together. And encrypted using,
很不幸，加密使用了相同的伪随机种子
unfortunately, the same pseudo-random
seed, in other words, using the same
也就是相同的流密钥
所以这里发生的
stream cipher key. So basically what's
happening here is you see an effect that
与二次密码本别无二致
客户端加密使用的一次密码本
the two time pad is taking place where the
set of messages from the client is
和服务端使用的一样
encrypted using the same one time pad as a
set of messages from the server. The
这里的教训是永远不要用相同密钥
lesson here is that you should never use
the same key to encrypt traffic in both
加密两个方向的流量
事实上，你需要一个密钥
directions. In fact, what you need to do
is have one key for interaction between
加密从客户端到服务端的信息
以及另一个密钥加密服务端到客户端
the client and the server and one key for
interaction between the server and the
我喜欢这样写，共享密钥k
client. The way I like to write this is
really that the shared key k really is a
其实是一对密钥，一个加密服务端到客户端
pair of keys. One key is used to encrypt
messages from server to client, and one
另一个加密客户端到服务端
key is used to encrypt messages from
client to server. So these are two
这里使用了两个不同的密钥
当然双方都知道这对密钥
separate keys that are used, and both
sides, of course, know this key. So both
双方都有这对密钥，对吧？
双方都可以进行加密
sides have this pair of keys, okay? and
they can both encrypt. So one is used to
一个加密一个方向，
另一个加密另一个方向
encrypt messages in one direction and one
is used to encrypt messages in the other
另一个二次密码本的重要例子
direction. So another important example of
the two time pad comes up in Wi-Fi
是在WiFi通信中，特别在802.11b协议中
communication, particularity in the 802.11b
protocol. So all of you I'm sure know that
802.11包含了一层加密层
最初的加密层叫做WEP
the 802.11 contains an encryption layer and
the original encryption layer was called
WEP对我们来说其实是一个很糟糕的协议
WEP and WEP fortunately for us is actually
a very badly designed protocol so that I
我总是拿它来当反面教材
can always use it as an example of how not
to do things. There are many, many
WEP包含很多很多错误
这里举它二次密码本的例子
mistakes inside of WEP and here I want to
use it as an example of how the two time
我解释一下WEP的工作原理
WEP中，有一个客户端
pad came about. So let me explain how WEP
works. So in WEP, there's a client and,
和一个接入点。这是客户端
这是接入点
and access point. Here's the client,
here's the access point. They both share a
它们共享一个密钥K。然后
当它们想相互通信时
secret key K. And then, when they wanna
transmit a message to one another. Say
它们互相传递帧
these are frames, that they
transmit to one another. Let's say the
(frame: 帧，一种数据报文)
比如客户端想发送一个包含明文M
的帧给接入点
client wants to send a frame containing
the plain text M to the access point, what
他首先要把一些校验和附在明文后面
he would do is first of all he appends
some sort of check sum to this plain text.
这里校验和并不重要
The check sum is not important at this
point, what is important is then this new
重要的是然后使用流密码加密
calculation gets encrypted using a stream
cypher where the stream cypher key is this
这里流密钥是一个值IV和一个长期的密钥K
的联结，这个IV为24位字符串
concatenation of a value IV and a long
term key K. So this IV is a 24 bit string.
好，这个IV为24位字符串
可知它从0开始取值
Okay, this IV is a 24 bit string, and you
can imagine that it starts from zero and
它可以是一个数据包的计数器
perhaps it's a counter that counts
increments by one for every packet. The
它们这样做的原因是，WEP的设计者们
知道在流密码中
reason they did this was the designers of
WEP realized that in a stream cypher, the
一个密钥只能加密一个明文信息
key is only supposed to be used to encrypt
one message. So they said well, let's go
那么就每帧使用不同的密钥吧
ahead and change the key after every
frame. And the way they changed the key
它们改变密钥的方法是
把这个IV放在密钥前面
essentially was by prepending this IV to
it. And you notice this IV changes on
每个数据包的IV不同，于是每个数据包
的IV加一。这个想法
every packet. So it increments by one on
every packet. And the idea, then, is sent
然后就直接发送密文
接收方也知道密钥K
in the clear along with the cipher text.
So the recipient knows the key K. He knows
也知道IV，就能通过联结IV和K
来重新推出PRG来
what the IV is. He can rederive the PRG
of IV concatenating K. And then decrypts
然后就能解密密文，还原明文M了
the cipher text to recover the original
message M. Now the problem with this
当然，问题在于IV只有24位
也就是说只有2的24次方个
of course is the IV is only 24 bits long.
Which means that there are only two to the
可能的IV，也就是说，
经过1600万帧的传输后
24 possible IV's. Which means that after
sixteen million frames are transmitted.
IV又要重0开始循环了
每经过1600万帧循环一次
Essentially the IV has to cycle. And once
it cycles after 16 million frames.
这就有了二次密码本
同样的IV被用来
Essentially we get a two time pad. The
same IV will be used to encrypt two
加密两个不同的信息，密钥K不变
它是一个长期的密钥
different messages. The key K never changes.
It's a long term key. And as a result,
于是，相同的密钥，即IV联结K
会被用来加密两个不同的帧
that same key, namely the IV concatenated K
would be used to encrypt two different
然后攻击者可以解出两个帧来
frames, and the attacker can then figure
out the plain text of both frames. So
这是一个问题，更严重的问题是
在很多802.11片上系统里
that's one problem. And the worst problem
is in fact that on many 802.11 cards, if
如果你重启系统，IV会被重置到0
you powercycle the card, the IV will reset
back to zero. And as a result, everytime
于是，每次重启系统，你会使用
you powercycle the card, essentially
you'll be encrypting the next payload
0联结K来加密下一个数据包
每次重启，你都要使用
using zero concatenated K. So after every
powercycle, you'll be using the zero
0联结K来加密许多报文
concatenated K key to encrypt many, many,
many times the same packets. So you see
所以在WEP中，同样的密码本会被用来
加密许多不同的信息
how in WEP, the same pad could be used to
encrypt many different messages as soon as
只要IV被重置。我们无法防止重启后
IV被重置的现象
the IV is repeated. There is nothing to
prevent the IV from repeating after a
或者1600万帧后归零
powercycle. Or am repeating after every
sixteen million frames which isn't that
1600万帧在忙碌的网络中并不算多
我们在讨论WEP
many frames in a busy network. So while we
are talking about WEP. I want to mention
我还会提到WEP的更多错误
这个错误确实挺严重
one more mistake that was done in WEP.
This is a pretty significant mistake and
我们来看如何更好地设计它
大家注意到WEP的设计者
let's see how we might design it better.
So you notice that the designers of WEP
想为每个数据包使用不同的密钥
basically wanted to use a different key
for every packet. Okay. So every frame is
每个帧使用不同密钥加密
即不同的IV和K的联结
encrypted using a different key
is concatonation of IV and K.
很遗憾，它们没有随机选取密钥
Unfortunately, they didn't randomize the
keys and the keys are actually, if you
如果单看第一帧的密钥
look at the key for frame number one,
well, you know, it will be this
它一定会是1与K的联结
我们刚刚提到这24位IV
concatenation of one and k. We'll just
feel this 24 bits. Then the key for frame
第二帧的密钥是2和K的联结
number two is the concatenation of two and
k. The key for frame number three is the
第三帧的密钥是3和K的联结
所以这些密钥之间非常接近
concatenation of three and k. So the keys
are very closely related to one another.
我还应该提到这些密钥本身可以是104位
And I should probably mention also that
these keys themselves can be 104 bits so
PRG生成密钥实际上是104+24=128位
that the resulting PRG key is actually
104 plus 24 bytes which is 128 bytes.
很不幸，这些密钥之间太过相近
Unfortunately these keys are very much
related to one another. These are not
它们并不是随机密钥。大家注意到
它们的后缀104位都是一样的
random keys. You notice they all have the
same suffix of 104 bytes. And it turns out
事实上WEP里的伪随机密钥
并没有设计得很安全
the pseudo-random generator used in WEP is
not designed to be secure when you use
你使用了相近的密钥
换句话说，大部分密钥之间
related keys that are so closely related.
In other words, the majority of these keys
基本上是一样多。事实上
对于WEP中的PRG
are basically the same. And in fact, for
the PRG that's used in WEP. That PRG is
叫做RC4。我们下一节会讲到它
called, RC 4. We'll talk about that
more in the next segment. It turns out
对其有一个有效攻击，
由Fluhrer, Mantin, Shamir三人
there's an attack. It was discovered by
Fluhrer, Mantin and Shamir
于2001年发现，证实经过10的6次方
back in 2001, that shows that after about
ten to the six of, after about a million
约一百万帧后，你就可以还原密钥了
frames. You can recover the secret key.
Can recover key. So, this is kind of a
这是个很严重的攻击，你只需要
监听一百万帧就可以了
disastrous attack that says essentially
all you have to do is listen to a million
刚才说了，这些帧全部由一个种子生成
frames. These frames basically, as we said
they're all generated from a very common
104位是全部一样的
seed, namely a 104 bits of these seeds are
all the same. The fact that they've used
这足以还原出密钥了
such closely related keys is enough to
actually recover the original key. And it
事实上经历了2001年的攻击
又涌现出了更好的攻击方案
turns out even after the 2001 attack,
better attacks have come out that show
证实了这种密钥关联是灾难性的
that these related keys are very much
disastrous and in fact these days
最近又发现四万帧就足以破解
something like 40,000 frames are
sufficient. And so that, within a matter
几分钟内，你就可以还原任何WEP网络
所使用的密钥了
of minutes, you can actually recover the
secret key in any WEP network. So
所以WEP无法提供任何的安全性
原因有二：第一
WEP provides no security at all
for two reasons. First of all, it can
它像二次密码本一样脆弱
更重要的，由于这些密钥
resolve in the two time pad. But more
significantly, because these keys are so
互相之间紧密关联，仅监听少量密文
就足以还原密钥
closely related, it's actually possible to
recover the key by watching just a few
顺便说下，当我们对加密机制里的步骤
cipher texts. And by the way, we'll see
that well, when we do a security analysis
进行安全分析时，在下几节里
我们会开始讨论如何分析
of these steps of constructions. In a few
segments, we'll start talking about how to
加密机制里的步骤。我们将看到
analyze these steps of constructions.
We'll see that when we have related keys
这样紧密关联的密钥事实上会导致
我们的安全分析失败
like this, in fact, our security analysis
will fail. We won't be able to get the
我们无法完成安全性证明
所以WEP设计者们应当怎么办？
proof to go through. So one could ask what
should the designers of a WEP should have
一个方法是对帧进行处理
done, instead? Well, one approach is to
basically treat the frames, you know M1,
M1, M2, M3每一帧都由客户端发向服务端
M2, M3. Each, each one is a separate frame
transmitted from the client to the server.
我们可以当成一个长流处理
He could have treated them as one
long stream, and then XOR them
然后进行异或操作，对长流
使用伪随机数发生器
potentially. Using the pseudo random
generator as one long stream. So the first
密码本的第一节用来加密M1
segment of the pad would have been used to
encrypt M1. The second
密码本的第二节用来加密M2
segment of the pad would have been used to
encrypt M2. The third segment
密码本的第三节用来加密M3，等等
of the pad would have been used to encrypt
M3. And so on and so forth.
所以设计者们本来就不应该
对每一帧都改变密钥
So they basically could never have had to
change the key because the entire
因为整个会话应被视为长流
但是他们为每一帧选不同的密钥
interaction is viewed as one long stream.
But they chose to have a different key for
如果你想那么做，有更好的办法
every frame. So if you want to do that, a
better way to do that is, rather than
不是小改IV，不是小改PRG密钥前缀
slightly modifying this IV that just
slightly modifies the prefix of the key,
更好的办法是再次使用PRG
of the PRG key. A better way to do that is
to use a PRG again. So essentially, what
这样你可以获得一个长期密钥
然后把密钥输入给PRG
you could do is you will take your long
term key. And then feed that directly
现在我们得到了一个长流
而且它看起来很随机的
through a PRG. So now we get a long stream
of bits that look essentially random.
可以使用最初的密码本分段
第一段可以当作密钥
And then the initial segment could be
used, the first segment could be used as
来加密第一帧。第二段当作密钥
the key, for frame number one. And then the
second segment would be used as the key
来加密第二帧，等等
for, you know, key for frame number two.
And so on and so forth. The third segment
第三段加密第三帧，等等
would be used to encrypt frame #three and
so on and so forth, okay? So the nice
这样一来每一帧都有一个伪随机密钥了
thing about this is now, essentially, by
doing this, each frame has a pseudo-random
这些密钥之间没有关系了
它们看起来像是随机密钥
key. These keys, now, have no relation to
one another. They look like random keys.
于是，如果PRG对随机密文C是安全的
它对输入也是安全的
And as a result, if the PRG is secure for
random Cs, it was also be secure on this
因为密钥看起来互相之间是独立的
input. Because these keys essentially look
as though they're independent of one
等我们讨论加密机制类型时
我们再来形式化地看如何分析这些
another. We'll see how to do this analysis
formally once we talk about these types of
由于二次密码本攻击很常用
constructions. Since this two-time pad
attack comes up so often in practice, it's
这也是个常见错误
这个例子就是想让大家避免之
such a common mistake, I want to give one
more example where it comes up so you know
我的最后一个例子是关于硬盘加密的
how to avoid it. The last example I want
to give is in the context of disk
设想我们有一文件
encryption. So imagine we have a certain
file and maybe the file begins with, you
文件以"给Bob的话"开头
后面跟着文件内容
know, the words to Bob. And then the
content of the file follows when this is
内容存在硬盘上，当然
文件从这里的硬盘里读取
stored on disk of course the file is gonna
get so here we have our disk here, the
文件被分块放置，对每一块
file is going to get broken into blocks.
And each block will be, you know, when we
当我们把分块存放在硬盘上时
就会对其进行加密
actually store this on a disk, you know,
things will be encrypted. You know, so
那么Bob可能会看第一分块
余下内容在剩下分块里
maybe to Bob will go into the first block
and then the rest of the content will go
当然这全被加密了
into the remaining blocks. But of course
this is all encrypted so I'll kind of use
我用这些线表示这被加密了
these lines here to denote the fact that
this is encrypted. And an attacker looking
一个攻击者来看硬盘
却无法知道文件内容是什么
at the disk has no idea what the contents
of the message is. But now suppose that at
假设经过一段时间后，用户做出修改
比如使用了编辑器
a later time, user goes ahead and
modifies, basically fires up the editor.
它修改了文件，现在不再是给Bob，而是要给Eve了
It modifies the file, so now instead of
saying to Bob, it says to Eve. And nothing
文件其余内容不变，仅改变接收方
else changes in the file, that's the only
change that was made. When the user then
然后用户把修改好的文件存到硬盘里
还要再加密一次
saves this modified file to disk,
basically he's gonna re encrypt it again.
同样的事情又要发生一遍
文件又会被分块
And so the same thing is gonna happen. The
file is gonna get broken into blocks. You
现在文件是给Eve的，一切都被加密
know, now the file's gonna say to Eve. And
everything, of course, is gonna be
我又在这写下这些线。现在攻击者来看硬盘了
encrypted. So again, I'll, put these lines
here. Now an attacker looking at the disc,
在用户修改前对原内容做了保存
现在攻击者又来看修改后的内容
taking a snapshot of the disc before the
edits. And then looking again at the disc
他会发现改变的仅仅是
after the edits. What he will see is that
the only thing that changed is this little
这一小段不一样了，其他地方都是一模一样的
segment here. That's now different.
Everything else looks exactly the same. So
即使攻击者不知道文件如何修改的
the attacker, even though he doesn't know
what actually happened to the file within
他却知道修改的严格位置
the file or what changed, he knows exactly
the location where the edits took place.
事实上，一次性密码本或
流密码一次加密一位
And so the fact that the one-time pad or
a stream cypher encrypts one bit at a time
意味着如果一处发生变化，
很容易分辨出发生改变的位置
means that if one change takes place, then
it's very easy to tell where that change
这就泄露了攻击者不应知道的信息
occurred instantly. That leaks information
that the attacker shouldn't actually
理想地，即使文件有一丁点改动
learn. Ideally you'd like to say that even
if the file changed just a little bit.
整个文件的加密结果都能被改变
或者至少所有分块内容都能有所改变
Entire contents of the file should change.
Or maybe at least the entire contents of
这里攻击者甚至知道改变
the blocks should change. Here you can see
the attacker even knows within the block
发生在哪一个分块，事实上
正因如此，在硬盘上使用流密码
where the change was actually made, okay.
So in fact, because of this, it's usually
不是一个好点子，本质上
a bad idea to use stream cyphers for disk
encryption. And essentially this is
这是二次密码本攻击的又一个例子
因为相同的密码本被用来
another example of a two-time pad attack
because the same pad is used to encrypt
加密两条不同的信息，似曾相识
two different messages. This, they happen
to be very similar, but nevertheless these
确是两条不同的信息
攻击者可以学到改变了什么
are two different messages, and the
attacker can learn what the change was and
他还可能知道内容如何改变的
in fact he might be able to even learn
what the actual changed words were, as a
所以这里的教训是，加密硬盘时
我们需要做些不同的工作
result of this. Okay, so the lesson here
is generally we need to do something
在后面的章节里我们再来讨论硬盘加密
different for disk encryption. We'll talk
about what to do for disk encryption in a
但是一次性密码本绝对不是
later segment, but essentially the
one-time pad is generally not a good idea
硬盘加密的好方法
那么再总结一下二次密码本攻击
for encrypting blocks on disks. So just
again to summarize the two-time pad
如你所想，我希望我已说服你
attack, we saw that you're supposed, I
hope I've convinced you that you're never
千万不要重复使用流密钥
ever, ever supposed to use a stream cypher
key more than once. Even though there are
即使有先例，你也需要小心
natural settings where that might happen,
you have to take care and make sure that
确保不要重复使用同样的密钥。对于网络流量
you're not using the same key more than
once. So for network traffic typically
每个会话有自己的密钥
what you're supposed to do is every
session would have its own key. Within the
会话内从客户端到服务端的信息
可视为一个完整流
session the message from the client and
the server look as one complete stream. It
它可只使用一个密钥加密
从服务端到客户端的信息
would be encrypted using one key. Is, the
messages from the server to the client
可被视为一个流并使用不同密钥加密
would be treated as one stream and
encrypted using a different key. And then
然后这个加密一般不使用流密码
for this encryption typically would not
use a stream cypher because, as changes
因为对文件的修改，会泄露文件内容
are made to the file, he would be leaking
information about the contents of the
好，我们的二次密码本的讨论完结了
file. Okay, so that concludes our brief
discussion of the two time pad.
下面我谈一个攻击
即事实上，一次性密码本
Next attack I want to mention. Is a fact
that the one time pad and stream cyphers
和流密码不提供完整性保护
它们所做的仅仅是
in general provide no integrity at all.
All they do is they try to provide
私密性保护，当密钥只用一次时
它们根本不提供完整性
confidentiality when the key's only used
once. They provide no integrity at all but
更糟的是，实际上很容易修改密文
even worse than that it's actually very
easy to modify cypher text and have known
来对还原明文造成显著影响
让我来解释一下
effects on the corresponding plain text.
So let me explain what I mean by that.
顺便说下，这个性质叫可修改性
This property, by the way, is called
malleability, and we'll see what I mean by
我们待会将看到。设想有明文M被加密
that in just a second. So imagine we have
some message M that gets encrypted. So,
使用流密码加密，当然
here, it gets encrypted using a stream
cipher. And the cipher text, of course, is
密文为M异或密钥K
现在一攻击者截获了密文
then gonna be, M XOR a K. Now an
attacker intercepts the cypher text. Well,
他还不知道密文是什么
不过除了窃听以外
that doesn't tell him what's, what the
plain text is but what he can do is now
攻击者还可以积极篡改密文
beyond eavesdropping he can actually
become an active attacker and modify the
当我可以篡改密文时
cypher text. So when I say modify the
cypher text let's suppose that he
假设他将密文和一特定值P异或
P叫做子置换密钥
XOR the cypher text with a certain
value P. Whats called a sub-permutation key.
这样密文就变成了M异或K异或P
Well, the resulting cipher text then
becomes M XOR K, XOR P. So now I'll
我问大家，当我们解密时
我们能得到什么？
ask you, when we decrypt the cipher text,
what is it going to decrypt to? Well I
大家应该会操作异或
解密后是M异或P
hope everybody sees manipulating the XORs
Basically the decryption becomes M XOR P
注意到异或密码本P后
So you notice that by XOR with this
pad P, the attacker was able to
攻击者可以对明文造成特定影响
have a very specific effect on the
resulting plain text. Okay. So a summary
总结一下，大家可以修改密文
这些修改将不会被检测出来
is basically you can modify the cypher
text. These modifications are undetected.
更糟的是，它们无法检测
它们对还原的明文有特定影响
But even worse, they're undetected, they
have a very specific impact on the
不管拿什么跟密文异或
resulting plain text. Namely whatever you
XOR the cipher text with is going to have
都会对明文产生影响
看得出这是危险的
that exact effect on the plain text. So to
see where this can be dangerous, let's
我们看一个特别的例子
假设用户发送了份Email
look at a particular example. Suppose the
user sends an email that starts with the
以“自Bob”开头，攻击者截获了密文
words from Bob. In the attacker
intercepts the corresponding cypher text.
他不知道明文是什么
He doesn't know what the cypher text is
but let's just for the sake of it let's
(口误cypher，应为plain)
不过我们不妨假定他知道这信来自Bob
pretend that he actually knows that this
message is actually from Bob. What he
他想修改密文，让明文变成
wants to do is he wants to modify the
ciphertext so that the plain text would
来自于另外某个人
比如说，他想让它变成
now look like it came from somebody else.
Say, he wants to make it look like this
这份信来自Alice。攻击者只有密文
message actually came from Alice. All he
has is the ciphertext. Well, what he can
(根据下文，此处应为Eve)
不过他可以异或特定的三个字母
do is he can XOR with a certain
three characters. We'll see
我们待会将看到是哪三个字母
what those three characters are in just a
second. And such that the resulting
这样子密文就变成从Eve发来的
ciphertext is actually an encryption of
the message from Eve. And so that now when
等用户解密时，他会认为这份信来自Eve
the user decrypts that. All of a sudden
he'll see, Hey, this message is from Eve.
来自Eve，而不是Bob
It's not, he'll think this message is from
Eve, not from Bob. And that might cause
明显有错误发生了
you know, the wrong thing to take place.
So here the attacker, even though he
即使攻击者自己不能创造密文
声称是来自Eve
himself could not have created a cypher
text that says from Eve, by modifying an
通过修改已有的密文
他也可以达到目的
existing cypher text all of a sudden he
was able to make the cypher text that he
密文必须被截获到，否则还做不了
could not have done without intercepting
at least one cypher text. So again by
截获一段密文，修改一下
就可以使其看起来是来自Eve
intercepting one cypher text he was able
to change it so now it looks like it's
而不是Bob。特别地
我们来看这三个字母是什么
from Eve, rather than from Bob. So just to
be specific, let's look what these three
我们看单词Bob，我用ASCII表示
characters need to be, so let's look at
the word Bob. And I'm going to write it in
Bob的ASCII码为十六进制42，6F和62
ASCII. So Bob in ASCII corresponds to 42
hex six f hex and 62 hex. So little b is
b=62H, o=6FH.单词Eve被编码成
encoded as 62, little o is encoded as six
f. The word eve is encoded as 45 hex, 76
(一般地，后缀H表十六进制)
45H, 76H和65H。当我异或这两个词时
我以字符串的形式进行异或
hex, and 65 hex. Now when I XOR these
two words, I'm literally going to XOR
Bob异或Eve，不难看出
them as bit strings. So Bob XOR eve,
it's not difficult to see that what I get
我得到了这三个字符07, 19, 07
are the three characters zero, seven.
Nineteen and 07. So really what these
就是简单的字符07, 19, 07
three characters here are going to be. Are
simply 07, nineteen, and 07. And by
在密文正确的位置异或这三个字母
XORing these three characters at the
right positions into the cipher text, the
攻击者可以将内容改成自Eve来
attacker was able to change the cipher
text to look like it came from Eve rather
而非Bob。这便是一例
than from Bob. So this is an example
where having a predictable impact on the
密文的可预测影响会导致问题
cipher text can actually cause quite a bit
of problems. And this is this property
这就是可修改性，我们说
一次性密码本是可修改的
called malleability. And we say that the
one time pad is malleable because it's
因为它的密文容易计算
将特定改变应用到明文上
very easy to compute in cipher texts, and
make prescribed changes to the
为了防止这点，我将花两三讲时间
corresponding plain text. So to prevent
all this, I'm gonna do that, actually, in
为大家展示如何为加密机制增加完整性
two or three lectures. And we're gonna
basically show how to add integrity to
这里我希望大家记住
encryption mechanisms in general. But
right now I want you to remember that the
一次性密码本本身是没有完整性保护的
对可修改密文的攻击者而言
one time pad by itself has no integrity
and is completely insecure against
它毫无安全性可言
attackers that actually modify the cipher
texts.